Finding Aid for Huron Valley Community Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1984-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Huron Valley Community Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1984-1994
Huron Valley Community Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
0.5 linear feet
952 Ba 2
Independent ecumenical church established in 1985 to minister to the gay and lesbian community of Ann Arbor, Michigan. Administrative and topical files include correspondence, newsletters and news clippings, church bulletins, and subject files detailing church activities; also scattered records of Metropolitan Christian Church, 1984-1985, some of whose members established Huron Valley Community Church.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (donor no. 8290 ) were donated by the Church in 1994.
The record group is open to research.
Huron Valley Community Church was formed in 1985 as an independent ecumenical church to minister to the lesbian and gay male communities of the Huron Valley area. Membership was drawn from a predecessor organization, the Metropolitan Christian Church. With the stated goal of achieving a fully inclusive Christian environment, participation by people from many different backgrounds, traditions, and belief systems was encouraged. Huron Valley Community Church was founded in the belief that God does not condemn all homosexual behavior. The Church affirms that homosexual relationships can be both wholesome and positive in the eyes of God and society.
Services began in area homes and were moved to the Green Glacier Community Center in 1986. From 1987 to 1993 the Church utilized the worship facilities of the Glacier Way United Methodist Church. Dissolution of Glacier Way United Methodist in 1993 resulted in relocation to the Good Shepherd Church of Ann Arbor.
Beginning in 1989, the congregation was significantly affected by debate over affiliation with the Universal Fellowship of Metropolitan Community Churches (FMCC), a national network of gay and lesbian ministries. Proponents of the plan stressed the benefits inherent in more consistent leadership, improved financial stability, and greater focus in the religious program. Opponents of affiliation sought to maintain the independence of Huron Valley Community Church. The issue was settled by a vote taken in 1992 which rejected affiliation by a slim margin. This led to a formal split within the congregation. The proponents of affiliation with FMCC formed a separate organization, Tree of Life Metropolitan Community Church. Huron Valley Community Church continues to function as an independent entity.
The records of Huron Valley Community Church are organized in a single alphabetical series of Administrative and Topical Files. The Administrative file, 1986-1994, provides insight into some of the special challenges faced by an alternative congregation, specifically the availability of suitable worship facilities. Information about Church functions and social activities may be found in the Program files, 1986-1994 and in the Church Sponsored Trip to Washington D.C. file, 1993. Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1994, are a rich source for information on subjects affecting the gay and lesbian community in Ann Arbor. Detailed information about efforts to combat the proposed amendment to the Michigan Constitution limiting legal protection for gay males and lesbians is available in the Constitutional Amendment file, 1993-1994. In addition, the Other Local Gay Groups files, 1985-1994, provide a glimpse of related organizations and activities in Michigan.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Church buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor; Gays--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor; Gays--Michigan--Ann Arbor; Huron Valley Community Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Metropolitan Christian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- Administrative & Topical Files
  - Metropolitan Christian Church (pre-HVCC), 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Administrative, 1986-1994 (Box 1)
  - Church Correspondence, 1986-1994 (Box 1)
  - Church Sponsored March on Washington D.C., Bus Trip, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Amendment, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Hymnal, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1985-1994
    - 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1994 (Box 1)
  - Program, 1986-1994
    - 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Social Action, Local, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Social Action, National, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Sunday Worship Bulletins, 1989-1994 (Box 1)